Hi guys!
I am Pranay
We are going to talk about
how to increase your bench press from
70 kgs to 100 kg-plus
that's fine with me. I'm kidding
We're going to talk about Benchmarks
like the life cycle of a benchmark
and what happens when a benchmark is
released and how people use it? How
do people to optimise for it?
so yeah
This is the second time that I'm doing this. So, the first time i
try to sell my product. So, this time
I'm going to try to
teach you something which you can only
take away from i know this is
And, this is something that is locked usually in
Frontier AI Labs
which is usually not accessible
When there is a Benchmark that is released,
what happens is people
first look at the types of tasks
that each Benchmark has.
And, then they realize:
Okay, does this task look like it's important to me?
Let's say - I am a Software Engineer. Or a Data Scientist
Is it important for me or for the Agent to be able to
Let's say- write python script or let's say write Model Architecture and stuff like that?
So, eventually what happens is
whenever a very good Benchmark comes out,
then, usually even a 2 points improvement on a benchmark. Like:
Let's say GPT 5.5 is 80% and Fable, I think is reported at 82%
And, with a 2% difference, you can raise like hundred Million
or something like that
So, what exactly is Benchmaxxxing?
Benchmaxxxing is like -
When there is a set of tasks and you have to increase
your performance on that task, or on those tasks.
So, there are a bunch of variables
that you can tune.
The Model is not the only variable,
the Harness, the Verification, the Tests- everything is part of that.
So, this is specifically
for Coding and Math Benchmarks - which are verifiable
in nature
Very briefly we are going to talk about the part
that i'm working on
my project which is basically on the
EVM Bench
like is based on smart contracts and
these smart contracts are basically deployed in
De-Fi, Social, Lending, AMMs and lot
of other applications. Like, these are called
Decentralised Applications
And, Smart Contracts- Ones who write them and they are deployed onto the BlockChain,
you can't change them. It's immutable code.
This EVM Bench - is basically a set of 120 tasks
across 40 different smart contracts.
And they're basically like a frontier
EVAL Benchmark release by OpenAI
And, what they are trying to figure out
is that why do models don't perform well?
We will see that in the
next few slides.
One thing I wanted to mention like I want to highlight here
is a Docker Local Chain.
What you'll see is that mostly in Coding Benchmarks,
what happens is
the structure is usually the same.
Like, there is always a separate environment.
Like, the Docker part is the grader.
and the evaluation and the execution all of it
happens in the Docker Container,
which is the environment.
So, then, while I was working on it
my setup was basically GPT 5.4
and Codex, and OpenCode
and I ran it across all of the EVM Bench tasks.
What i found out was that -
the results are pathetic!
And, Frontier Models are NOT that good!
I wanted to run this for Opus, but
but
every single task here takes
about two hundred to three hundred tool calls
not tool calls - API calls
And, it gets very expensive and they run for
one and a half, two hours. Each!
So, these would run overnight and
Thanks to Aditya (Adi)!
I've spent up more than like, two thousand dollars worth of
his compute on Azure credits.
Thanks Adi! :)
So, while i was trying
to figure out
how do I improve performance on EVM Bench,
I was trying to dive deeper
into it. So, frmo all of the traces that
I had this is what i found out:
This is basically the split - like the
distribution of what kind of tools does
the Agent call.
You can go to this QR code,
and look at like more insights there.
If you're trying to
increase your performance on some kind of a Coding Benchmark,
then these insights will definitely help you. So, you can check them out.
While i was trying to understand
the distribution here, I was looking at
other benchmarks
which also had the same structure
So, a very common one is - SWE Bench
and I was looking through SWE Bench
and then I found out this article
by OpenAI. And what it said is that -
Performance on SWE Bench - it does not tell you
about the Frontier capabilities of models. And, why is that?
That's simply because number of
tasks the and the type of
tasks that SWE Bench has,
there are too many similar tasks in the
Pre-Training and the Post-Training data. So,
they have been climbed upon so much
that you don't even need to
give them a question. Like, if you
just give them the Test
They will tell you the question and the answer.
which is very bad!
That's how they measured contamination in the Benchmark.
which is bad. They recommend SWE Bench Pro
which does not have these problems
I want you to think about it this way. If anything is verifyable,
and it is open source, people will be
able to figure out what
similar tasks to create so that you can
train on those new tasks
and then increase the capability on the
original task. While i was looking
through the distribution of SWE Bench- like how
Coding Models perform SWE Bench Tasks,
I found out that - this is the same
distribution across both EVM Bench Task and
SWE Bench Task, barring the on-chain state query
because SWE Bench does not
have on-chain state query.
This is only local to EVM Bench
But rest of it is basically the same. So,
remember
my objective here was to dive deep
and improve performance on EVM Bench
all I cared about. Okay? That is
not the right way by the way
that is all I care about
I think Paras helped me understand
why it is not the right way.
Because, improving
performance on a Benchmark does not
really prove that that is some
signs behind why those Benchmarks'
performance was improved. What it taught me was that that
If you can teach the model
the right type of localization, reproduction
editing and validation for a particular- let's say - Task type
then you don't really need to improve
general reasoning. It will just do. Like,
It will just be a parrot.
And it will do very well on the benchmarks
but it will not explicitly show who reasoning.
A very simple example of it is this :
If you look at Chinese Models. Have you used- MiniMax?
M 2.5?
not M 2.7 because that was
Post-Trained on something different. But MiniMax M 2.5 - if you use it,
It's performing like 75%
on SWE Bench. And if you compare
it to OPUS of that time,
OPUS was at around 78-79%
and if you try to talk
to that Model, it would be pathetic.
It would not know. It would answer even normal questions with code,
which is not okay!
But, people would only use MiniMax M 2.5
specifically for code
in a coding harness. as a coding agent.
Now
2 points: This is by the way
the creator of the SWE Bench
so basically he was asking - do we
Benchmaxxx on SWE Bench or any
kind of benchmark? Well, i think YES. Why? Because
think about- If the Chinese don't release
models which 1/10th the
price, then OpenAI and Anthropic
does not have any pressure here.
They've zero pressure to not increase the price.
So, then the 20$ subscription becomes
200$
And the 200$ subscription currently becaomes, let's say-
$10,000 Enterprise subscription
or something like that. So, this is
definitely useful.
But, the problems! The problems are because
as i said
The repos are public, the evaluations of public, and
the entire code patches,
everything is public. Like you can create
similar tasks that are in SWE Bench
and then you know match them to SWE Bench
you know like improve performance on SWE Bench.
Like, for example- let's say I have a Python repo, and it is
supposed to be some Django, REST API or something,
I can create something like, which also is a Django repo
But, it is doing -let's say- do list
or something
And if i train on
enough of these examples then I can improve
performance on SWE Bench without it being
part of the training.
A few months ago, the SWE Bench guys
released this, which is called: SWE Smith
This is interesting, because these guys
trained a 32B Model and
they were basically trying to scale the
amount of data for software engineering, and they used the same principles that I told you
Now, the performance here is 40.2% pass@1 on SWE Bench
which is right now like
any 32B Model right not can achieve that
because it is 10 months old.
So, the insight is not the performance, the insight is the RECIPE.
The recipe is basically this. So, what happens is8i999gggggggb=
you take a repo
like letter you have any benchmark for
or any task. Take that repo, and
you create an environmen. The environment is
basically an execution which gives feedback to
the agent. And, after that
you created Tests. These tests
are supposed to be extremely
expressive.
So, writing a very good test suite
is basically your insight - your moat.
- to actually doing automation.
If you can tell the agent-
whether you're trying to orchestrate
like a bunch of DevOps tasks or
let's say CI/SD pipelines or, let's say
you're trying to write some very specific code,
for a very specific client with
some SLAs, your objective is to
write tests in such scrutiny that
it should tell
the Agent what is wrong.
And, the agent is smart enough to fix it.
So, tests. Write the tests!
So, the 4th point
is basically - once you have written the
first three things, what you can
do is :
Ask an AI/LLM Model
able to able to make changes into it
Like, do mutations on let's say- whether the function
changes, or
like mutations on the abstract-syntax tree, and
extreme and then you can create like
of a bunch of tasks
for your repo, and then-
You can have a 32B
which performs like Claude Opus
on your Repo.
That's it, thank you!